Guide to the Orange A. Olsen Audio Visual Collection 1917-1945
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
Orange A. Olsen Audio Visual Collection
1926-1945
J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah Audio Visual Archives Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 801-581-8863 SPCreference@lists.utah.edu
A0912
Olsen, Orange A. 1890-1945
This collection consists of 48 16mm films, 3 miniDV tapes, 1 BetacamSP tape, and 1 DVD
The Orange A. Olsen collection provides a look into Utah National Forests between approximately 1926 and 1945 as filmed by Orange A. Olsen. The film clips feature a variety of animals and scenic locations, in addition to hunting and forests fires in the Utah wilderness.
Biographical Note
Orange A. Olsen was born October 10, 1890 with a twin named Henning. Both were named after their grandfathers, Utah pioneers Orange Seely and Henning Olsen. Their parents Abenadi and Hannah Seely Olsen raised them on a farm.
Olsen attended three years of high school in the Emery Stake Academy and, from 1910 to 1912, served as a missionary for the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints LDS mission in Germany, Switzerland, and Austria. Afterwards, he worked as a clerk in the Castle Dale Cooperative store (2 years), then as a bookkeeper for the Consolidated Wagon and Machine Company. He married Aileen Brown of Salt Lake City in 1915 and took a correspondence course in law.
Olsen began work with the Forest Service in November 1917 as a clerk in the Manti Supervisor’s Office in Ephraim. He was the Mammoth District Ranger (near Fairview) on the Manti from 1918 until 1922 when he became deputy forest supervisor. His next appointments were as forest supervisor of the Lemhi (1922-23), La Sal (1923-26), and Dixie (1926-31) national forests. In 1931, Olsen transferred to Region 4’s regional office in Ogden, Utah to head up the wildlife division. In order to regulate big game hunting and fishing activities in his region, he began conducting the annual wildlife census via aircraft. He was considered a pioneer in developing this new technique of the big game census. Unfortunately, he died in 1945 in an airplane crash while conducting an aerial count of elk in the Bridger National Forest.
Olsen was known for always carrying a videocamera with him. This audio visual collection consists of 16mm film clips of various Forest Service footage taken by Olsen during his time working for the Forest Service.
The Orange A. Olsen audio visual collection consists of film clips which feature a variety of animals and scenic locations, in addition to people enjoying outdoor activities in the Utah wilderness. All video has been digitized and is available on DVD in the Special Collections Reading Room.
Material is organized by subject matter. Approximate film dates determined by film edge codes, which identify the year the film stock was manufactured. A reasonable estimation of film date would be between the film stock manufacture year and the year of Olsens death, 1945.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.
Donated by Carole Gardner in 2006.
See the Orange A. Olsen Papers, 1945
Olsen, Orange A. 1890-1945; United States. Forest Service; Wildlife management -- Utah; Fisheries and Wildlife; Forestry and Forestry Products; Ogden; Moving Images
- Collection of 24 16mm Clips with Wildlife Footage, Undated
  - Clips of a Bull, American Badger, Pika, and a Beaver, Edge Code: 1926; 16mm Film Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 1)
  - Clips of Deer, Edge Code: 1938/1939; 16mm Film Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 2)
  - Clips of Deer in the snow, Edge Code: 1943; 16mm Film Color and Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 3)
  - Clips of Deer in the snow, Edge Code: 1938; 16mm Film Color and Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 4)
  - Clips of Deer, Edge Code: 1936; 16mm Film Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 5)
  - Clips of Elk, Edge Code: 1933; 16mm Film Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 6)
  - Clips of Elk, Edge Code: 1936; 16mm Film Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 7)
  - Clips of Elk and Deer, Edge Code: 1936; 16mm Film Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 8)
  - Clips of Scenic Views, Deer, and Moose, Edge Code: 1936; 16mm Film Color Film; No Sound (Reel 9)
  - Clips of Deer, Elk and Moose, Edge Code: 1932; 16mm Film Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 10)
  - Clips of Moose, Edge Code: 1933; 16mm Film Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 11)
  - Clips of Moose, Edge Code: 1933; 16mm Film Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 12)
  - Clips of Moose stuck in Mud, Edge Code: 1932; 16mm Film Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 13)
  - Clips of Moose stuck in Mud, Edge Code: 1932; 16mm Film Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 14)
  - Clips of a Robin, Birds, a Nest with Eggs, and Moose, Edge Code: 1939; 16mm Film Color and Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 15)
  - Clips of Buffalo, Elk, and a Geyser, Edge Code: 1942; 16mm Film Color Film; No Sound (Reel 16)
  - Clips of Elk, Squirrel, Rams, Mountain Goats, Olsen and Family, and Horses, Edge Code: 1943; 16mm Film Color Film; No Sound (Reel 17)
  - Clips of Scenic Views, and Rams, 12/7/1940; 16mm Film Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 18)
  - Clips of Rams, Edge Code: Undated; 16mm Film Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 19)
  - Clips of Black Bears with Cubs, and Moose, Edge Code: 1936; 16mm Film Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 20)
  - Clips of Ducks, Beaver, and Trapping, Edge Code: 1935; 16mm Film Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 21)
  - Clips of Birds, Edge Code: 1944; 16mm Film Color Film; No Sound (Reel 22)
  - Clips of a Grouse, Edge Code: 1936; 16mm Film Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 23)
  - Clips of Olsen inspecting Dead Animals and Antlers, Edge Code: 1941; 16mm Film Color Film; No Sound (Reel 24)
- Collection of 2 16mm Clips with Scenic View Footage, Undated
  - Clips of Scenic Views of Canyons and Nature, Edge Code: 1941; 16mm Film Color Film; No Sound (Reel 25)
  - Clips of Aerial Scenic Views, Edge Code: 1942; 16mm Film Color Film; No Sound (Reel 26)
- Collection of 7 16mm Clips with Hunting Footage, Undated
  - Clips of Grazing Cattle, Hunting for Deer on Horseback, and Big Game Hunting Regulation, Edge Code: 1941; 16mm Film Color Film; No Sound (Reel 27)
  - Clips of Olsen inspecting foliage, Elk and Deer, Tagging deer, Olsen walking in snowshoes, Hunting on Horseback, and Cattle, Edge Code: 1942; 16mm Film Color Film; No Sound (Reel 28)
  - Clips of a Hunter with Dead Game, Hunter Base Camp with Horses and Tents, Deer Herd, Aerial Footage of Mountains, and Wild Turkeys, Edge Code: 1942; 16mm Film Color Film; No Sound (Reel 29)
  - Clips of Scenic Views, Hunters inspecting Dead Game, Hunters on Horseback with Dead Game, Edge Code: 1932; 16mm Film Color Film; No Sound (Reel 30)
  - Clips of a Sign for "S and S Hunting Lodge," and Trucks driving in the Snow, Edge Code: 1941; 16mm Film Color Film; No Sound (Reel 31)
  - Clips of the Olsen Ranch, Hunters enjoying Food, Hunting Big Game in the Winter, Deer and Elk, Hunters on Horseback, 12/7/1940; 16mm Film Color Film; No Sound (Reel 32)
  - Clips of Elk Hunting on Horseback, Edge Code: 1941; 16mm Film Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 33)
- Collection of 11 16mm Clips with Forest Service Footage, Undated
  - Clips of Olsen walking in the Snow with Snowshoes, Edge Code: 1941; 16mm Film Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 34)
  - Clips of Forest Rangers building bridges and other structures out of Logs and Rocks, Edge Code: 1936; 16mm Film Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 35)
  - Clips of Scenic Views, the Forest Service building a bridge, and Ice Fishing by Olsen, Edge Code: 1938; 16mm Film Color Film; No Sound (Reel 36)
  - Clips of a Vehicle, Releasing Fish, Olsen and others overlooking an area on a Bridge, and throwing Rocks at Pikas, Edge Code: 1933; 16mm Film Color Film; No Sound (Reel 37)
  - Clips of releasing Fish into the wild, Edge Code: 1942; 16mm Film Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 38)
  - Clips of Scenic Views, and an Aerial Census, Edge Code: 1941; 16mm Film Color Film; No Sound (Reel 39)
  - Clips of an Aerial Census, Edge Code: 1936; 16mm Film Color Film; No Sound (Reel 40)
  - Clips of an Aerial Census and Footage of the Plane that was used, Edge Code: 1939/1940; 16mm Film Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 41)
  - Clips of Olsen inspecting foilage and taking notes, Edge Code: 1940; 16mm Film Color Film; No Sound (Reel 42)
  - Clips of Olsen inspecting Foilage, Clips of Deer, Forest Service Rangers on Horseback, Rangers inspecting dead and dying Game, Edge Code: 1937; 16mm Film Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 43)
  - Clips of various Forest Service activities including Forest Fighting, Logging, Animals, Hunting, and more, Edge Code: 1937; 16mm Film Black/White Film; No Sound (Reel 44)
- Collection of 2 16mm Clips with Forest Fire Footage, Undated
  - Clips of Forest Rangers creating a Sagebrush Fire, Edge Code: 1935; 16mm Film Color Film; No Sound (Reel 45)
  - Clips of Aerial Views of a Forest Fire, loading a Plane, ground footage of a Forest Fire, Group of People making a Firebreak, Basecamp, Edge Code: 1942; 16mm Film Color Film; No Sound (Reel 46)
- Collection of 2 16mm Clips with Home Video Footage, Undated
  - Clips of the Olsen Family enjoying the Utah Wilderness and Animals, and Olsen undertaking his Forest Service Duties, Edge Code: 1935; 16mm Film Color Film; No Sound (Reel 47)
  - Clips from a Family Trip including a Train ride through the Moffet Tunnel. *Note: Edgemark on film indicates that it was manufactured in 1950, five years after the death of Orange A. Olsen. This may be a reproduction of older footage before Olsen's death, or his family's footage after it. If it is after his death, the man who looks remarkably similar to Olsen may be his twin brother., Edge Code: 1942; 16mm Film Color Film; No Sound (Reel 48)
- Collection of 3 MiniDV tapes that are copies of all 16mm Footage, Undated
  - 01-35 of the 16mm film collection. Item numbers have since changed in order to better categorize footage by subject matter., MiniDV Tape Color and Black/White Footage; No Sound (Tape 1)
  - 36-42 of the 16mm film collection. Item numbers have since changed in order to better categorize footage by subject matter., MiniDV Tape Color and Black/White Footage; No Sound (Tape 2)
  - 43-48 of the 16mm film collection. Item numbers have since changed in order to better categorize footage by subject matter., MiniDV Tape Color and Black/White Footage; No Sound (Tape 3)
- BetaCamSP Tape copy of "Realm of the Wild"
  - "Realm of the Wild", MiniDV Tape Color Footage (Tape 1)
- DVD copy of "Realm of the Wild"
  - "Realm of the Wild", DVD Color Footage (Tape 1)